Fernanda Ramirez-Espinoza

Progress

Contact Pontificia Universidad Católica Phone/WhatsApp: (+56) 9 9969 1176

Information JPAL-LAC E-mail: maramirez@povertyactionlab.org

> Instituto de Economía WWW: www.ramirezespinoza.com

Av. Vicuña MacKenna 4860,

Santiago, Chile

Current JPAL-LAC — Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

APPOINTMENTS Postdoctoral Research Fellow Jun 2022 -

> Research Affiliate - ConsiliumBots Jan. 2020 -

> Social Impact Fellow – Agency Fund Dec. 2021-

EDUCATION Ph.D. Educational Policy and Program Evaluation, Harvard University May 2022

Committee: Eric Taylor (chair), Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Michela Carlana, Christopher Neilson

Master in Education – International Education Policy, Harvard University May 2021

Master in Public Policy, Harvard University May 2017

M.S. in Engineering Science, Applied Microeconomics, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile Maximum distinction Nov. 2011

B.S. in Industrial Engineering, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

Nov. 2010 Maximum Distinction

Diploma in Transportation Engineering, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

Maximum Distinction Nov. 2010

Research Labor Economics, Economics of Education, Applied Microeconomics, Educational Policy, Gender Interests

and Education, Program Evaluation.

"Gender Peer Effects in Post-Secondary Vocational Education" Research in

> "Gender Confidence Differences and the College Major Gap": Finished RCT, data analysis in progress (https://www.socialscienceregistry.org/trials/7229)

"Personalized Information Provision: Does Gender Play a Role?" (With Christopher Neilson)

"Closing Gaps in Higher Education Trajectories: The Effect of Targeted Information and Mentorship ": RCT in progress (with Andrés Fernández-Barrios)

"Textbook Gender Bias and Educational Gender Gap"

"Providing Relative Performance Information in Colombia: Effects on Beliefs".

"Do Cohort Peer Diversity Matters and For Whom? Evidence from Chile on Students' Academic Outcomes". (With Francisco Lagos)

"School admissions: Allocation Algorithms and Its Effects on school Segregation". (With Gabriel Gutirrez, Isidora Palma, and Francisco Lagos)

AWARDS, HONORS AND GRANTS

Social Impact Fellowship (\$65,000) - Agency Fund SPC (2021)

Independent Experience Stipend - David Rockefeller Center for Latin American Studies (2021)

Jens Aubrey Westengard Summer Research and Travel Grant, Harvard GSAS (2019)

Jens Aubrey Westengard Summer Research and Travel Grant, Harvard GSAS (2018)

Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Ph.D. Fellowship (2017–2019)

Carnesale Fellowship – Harvard Kennedy School (2015-2017)

Luksic Abaroa Fellowship for Chilean Students – Harvard Kennedy School (2015-2017)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE Inter-American Development Bank, Washington DC, USA

Education Division Research Consultant

September, 2019 - December 2020

Harvard University

Research Assistant - Professor Emmerich Davies

June, 2018 - Sept 2018

Harvard Graduate School of Education

Research Assistant - Professor Joshua Goodman

Harvard Kennedy School of Government

May 2018

Princeton University

Research Assistant - Professor Christopher Nielson Economics Department

June, 2016 - August 2016

Conference and Presentations

STEM Gender Peer Effects in Post-Secondary Vocational Education:

- (Scheduled): Universidad del Pacífico (Perú), Seminario de Economía. December 2021.
- (Scheduled): Universidad Diego Portales, Seminario de Economía. Diciembre 2021.
- Graduate Students in Economics of Education (GEEZ), Zoom Seminar. November 2021.
- Ciclo de Seminario Económicos, FEN, Universidad de Talca. November, 2021
- Ridge LACEA Labor, Online (Covid-19), 9-10 December, 2020.
- Encuentro Sociedad Chilena de Políticas Públicas, Santiago, Chile, January 2020.
- (Cancelled due to COVID-19): Society for Research on Educational Effectiveness (SREE), Arlington, Virginia, USA, March, 2020.
- (Cancelled due to COVID-19): Association for Education Finance and Policy (AEFP), Fort Worth, Texas, USA, March, 2020.
- Association for Public Policy Analysis & Management (APPAM), Denver, Colorado, USA, November, 2019.
- Harvard Graduate School of Education Doctoral Colloquium, Harvard University, October 2019.

Information provision and STEM enrollment

- (Scheduled) Association for Public Policy Analysis & Management (APPAM), Austin, TX, USA, November 2021.
- Harvard Graduate School of Education Doctoral Colloquium, Harvard University, October 2021.

Gender Bias in Textbooks:

Association for Public Policy Analysis & Management (APPAM), Online, March 27-29 2021.

Socioeconomic Diversity Peer Effects:

 American Educational Research Association (AERA) Annual Meeting, Online, April 8-12, 2021.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Instructor, Harvard Graduate School of Education

- Educational Policy in Developing Countries: Reviewing Impact Evaluations (Spring '22)

Teaching Fellow, Harvard Graduate School of Education

- Using Data in Organization (Prof. Carrie Conaway, Spring '21)
- The Politics of Education in Developing Countries (Prof. Emmerich Daviers, Fall '20)
- Applied Data Analysis (Prof. Andrew Ho, Spring '20)
- Microeconomics of Education (Prof. F. Barrera-Osorio, Fall '18 & Fall '19)
- The Consequences of Educational Policy Interventions in Developing Countries (Prof. F. Barrera-Osorio, Spring '19)

Teaching Assistant, Kennedy School of Government (9/2017 - 12/2017)

- Economic Analysis of Public Policy (Prof. Mark Shepard, Spring '17)

Teaching Fellow, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile (2007 – 2010

- Optimization (2009-2010, 4 semesters)
- Introduction to Economics (2007-2008, 3 semesters)
- Calculus II (2007, 1 semester, Instituto de Economía)

SERVICE

Research Doctoral Advice Committee (2019-2020)

Founder and President of the Harvard Association of Chilean Students (2018-2019) Founder and President of the Chilean Caucus (Harvard Kennedy School) (2017-2018)

Professional Experience Chief of Mission, Fundación América Solidaria, Port Au Prince, Haiti (2014 - 2015)

Cofounder and Board Member, Fundación Educación 2020, Santiago, Chile (August, 2012 - Jan, 2014)

Staff Professional - Plan de Formación de Directores de Excelencia, Ministry of Education, Santiago, Chile (2012)

OTHER SKILLS

Programming languages: R, Stata, LATEX.

Languages: Spanish (Native), English (Fluent), Portuguese (Intermediate), Haitian Creole (Basic), French (Basic).

References

Eric Taylor, Associate professor, Harvard Graduate School of Education (eric_taylor@gse.harvard.edu)

Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Associate Professor of Public Policy, Education and Economics, Vanderbilt University (felipe.barrera.-.osorio@vanderbilt.edu)

Christopher Neilson, Assistant Professor of Economics at Princeton (cneilson@princeton.edu)